<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Posts on BrentBoyMeBlog</title><link>https://bbmb.me/posts/</link><description>Recent content in Posts on BrentBoyMeBlog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>brent.monning.jr@gmail.com (Brent Monning)</managingEditor><webMaster>brent.monning.jr@gmail.com (Brent Monning)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2022 15:04:26 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://bbmb.me/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Is it necessary for Apple to 'fix messaging?'</title><link>https://bbmb.me/posts/rcs-apple/</link><pubDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2022 15:04:26 -0700</pubDate><author>brent.monning.jr@gmail.com (Brent Monning)</author><guid>https://bbmb.me/posts/rcs-apple/</guid><description>Context Recently, Google has pushed out a campaign directly against Apple, known as &amp;ldquo;Get the message.&amp;rdquo; If you&amp;rsquo;re aware of the &amp;ldquo;blue bubble, green bubble&amp;rdquo; drama between iPhones and Android phones before, this is exactly about that. If you&amp;rsquo;re out of the loop, when a message is sent from iMessage (their own proprietary messaging protocol), your bubbles turns blue, indicating that your messages are encrypted. When the messages are sent through the outdated SMS protocol, which has been used for years and is not secured or encrypted in the slightest, your bubble turns green.</description><content>&lt;h3 id="context">Context&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Recently, Google has pushed out a campaign directly against Apple, known as &amp;ldquo;Get the message.&amp;rdquo; If you&amp;rsquo;re aware of the &amp;ldquo;blue bubble, green bubble&amp;rdquo; drama between iPhones and Android phones before, this is exactly about that. If you&amp;rsquo;re out of the loop, when a message is sent from iMessage (their own proprietary messaging protocol), your bubbles turns blue, indicating that your messages are encrypted. When the messages are sent through the outdated SMS protocol, which has been used for years and is not secured or encrypted in the slightest, your bubble turns green. Android phones do not support iMessage due to it&amp;rsquo;s proprietary nature, and because of that, when a message is sent between an Android phone and an iPhone, your messages in that conversation are green from the iPhone.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>SMS has a ton of disadvantages compared to iMessage, it is specific to cellular connections (it is incompatible with internet texting), group texts are much more rudimentary, media is typically extremely compressed, it is unencrypted as mentioned before, but the big thing Google is making a big deal about is the green bubbles comparitively to the blue bubbles (even if they try to make it look like they are not talking about this, don&amp;rsquo;t fall for it.) These are only some of the flaws, and as such, Google has invented a new open protocol known as RCS. It is meant to be a much more modern protocol to SMS, but unlike iMessage, it isn&amp;rsquo;t closed off to Apple devices, and it attempts to fix many of the issues with SMS as with iMessage.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This isn&amp;rsquo;t the first time this has been addressed before, it is just that companies like Google are starting to notice the importance of such protocols. There are still alternatives. Internet messanging chats, such as Discord, WhatsApp, and even Google&amp;rsquo;s own Chat (also known as Hangouts) are fantastic alternatives. But they don&amp;rsquo;t integrate with your phone whatsoever, and they&amp;rsquo;re all competing, which means that they&amp;rsquo;re isolated to the people who use those services. Signal attempts to be a solution to this; a very similar premise to iMessage, but also more open and adapted, for example, all messages are fully encrypted between devices using Signal. The problem with Signal is that it isn&amp;rsquo;t a standard, and it requires you to download it&amp;rsquo;s app, both ends have to be using it, which means you&amp;rsquo;ll need to get the other end to run Signal as well. RCS is a standard made by Google, which means a big chunk of Android devices will adapt to it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But the general problem Google is making a big fuss about is that Apple will not adapt to the shiny new RCS standard. They are sticking purely with iMessage, which means it&amp;rsquo;s still a game of &amp;ldquo;blue bubble, green bubble.&amp;rdquo; But is Google in the right? Here are my thoughts.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="yays-to-implement-rcs">Yays (to implement RCS)&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>First of all, I&amp;rsquo;ll give my thoughts in favor of Google. For one, here&amp;rsquo;s something that wasn&amp;rsquo;t mentioned that can be a genuinely compelling pro. Not every country or carrier is in support of these newer protocols, which is what happened with MMS, because they weren&amp;rsquo;t used often, which didn&amp;rsquo;t give much insentive for the carriers to continue. RCS could fix this, especially in areas with weak cellular connections, but higher local WiFi connections. The higher possibility of accessibility is a big plus in my book.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Whilst typically unimportant, I will say that higher fidelity media files are quite a good pro if done well, as I can definitely notice compression between SMS files. Fixes for group chat, and &amp;ldquo;de-crapifying&amp;rdquo; it is also a step in the right direction, as SMS is quite bad in that regard. But that&amp;rsquo;s really about it. Other than that, there&amp;rsquo;s not many advantages. I hoped it wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be this short of a list, but onwards.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="nays-to-not-implement-rcs">Nays (to not implement RCS)&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Here&amp;rsquo;s the big issue I notice in particular. Privacy is a huge concern nowadays, and Google tries to make it seem like in the article that RCS is secure in the regard that it uses End to End (E2E) encryption. &lt;strong>More likely than not, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t. If anything, it can be as insecure as SMS at times.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Group chats are fully unsecured and unencrypted, period. They said they would implement it &amp;ldquo;later this year&amp;rdquo; in beta. That&amp;rsquo;s like if Taco Bell had put up an advertisement for a special that isn&amp;rsquo;t going to be sold until the next year. If Google is going to try and push Apple to adopt this standard, it better not be half baked, especially when improved group chats is a big point. E2E is only supported on one to one chats.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To add, E2E in RCS is only implemented if both clients support it. Google Messages does support RCS encryption (which to be fair, is the most used client on Android), but most other messaging clients that support RCS don&amp;rsquo;t. Not to mention, Google has a pretty bad track record with privacy in general, often collecting as much data from you as possible.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There&amp;rsquo;s also the fact that Google has been trying to create a chat solution for many years, and they always seem to screw it up in some way or another. Google Chat / Hangouts didn&amp;rsquo;t work out that well, presumably with being locked into Google services such as the former Google+ and lacking essential features, as well with many killed off services such as Allo, Spaces, and Talk. Are these guys really the correct people to pull this off?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Also, there are so many things wrong with Google&amp;rsquo;s arguments for RCS in general. Along with the fact that a big chunk of the arguments seem like just nitpicks in general, Google says that the green bubbled messages are hard to read. For one, the message bubble colors are from your end, not from the other person&amp;rsquo;s end, which are black on light gray. The green used as an example is also the more pastel Material Design green. In general, it just seems like an attempt to make Apple look bad, I guess to try and &amp;ldquo;convince&amp;rdquo; them?&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Trying to win people over with statements like &amp;ldquo;People are talking about it. From tweets to TikToks the conversation is bubbling&amp;rdquo;, and citing Wall Street Journal headlines like &amp;ldquo;Why Apple’s iMessage is winning: Teens dread the green text bubble&amp;rdquo; just seems desperate and edgy in general. I feel like Google is trying to just appear as the &amp;ldquo;heroes&amp;rdquo; of this unnecessary topic, because if anything, it just seems like a big trendy attempt to spread their shiny new protocol, after being so disorganized before.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>That being said, I can still somehow see Apple adding RCS to their Messages app as an option, since it is a newer protocol with more modern features. However, I don&amp;rsquo;t expect the messages to be blue. They&amp;rsquo;d likely still be green, or possibly even some other color. To me, the blue bubbles are merely an indication of if one is using iMessage or not, which only just tells me if my messages are encrypted or not, but nobody should gatekeep their digital social circle just because their friends don&amp;rsquo;t have a grand to burn on their phone. In conclusion, who in the living hell cares about the difference between green and blue?&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="credits">Credits&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.android.com/get-the-message/">https://www.android.com/get-the-message/&lt;/a>
&lt;a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/zakdoffman/2021/02/27/google-android-messages-update-apple-iphone-ipad-imessage-security-versus-sms-rcs-and-whatsapp-encryption/">https://www.forbes.com/sites/zakdoffman/2021/02/27/google-android-messages-update-apple-iphone-ipad-imessage-security-versus-sms-rcs-and-whatsapp-encryption/&lt;/a>
&lt;a href="https://9to5google.com/2022/05/11/google-messages-rcs-group-encryption/">https://9to5google.com/2022/05/11/google-messages-rcs-group-encryption/&lt;/a>&lt;/p></content></item></channel></rss>